<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<root>
	<Defective_Dual_Cerebellum type="str">The character has a second brain that hinders his thought
processes. This brain has 1d4 mental mutations of its own
(half of which should be defects, round up), which should
be kept secret from the player until an opportunity to
discover them comes about during play. This second brain
may have an entirely different personality and motives than
the character, and may try to foil the character’s actions at
inconvenient times. This is up to the ML’s discretion. This
“Hyde” brain may attempt to take over the mutant’s body,
as the mutation possession, once per month for a duration
of 24 hours.
</Defective_Dual_Cerebellum>
	<Pain_Insensitivity type="str">The character lacks the awareness that living creatures
normally possess with regard to their bodies and
immediate surroundings. The character does not feel pain
when injured, even if a weapon has penetrated his body.
The character will not be able to tell how much damage
he has sustained without making a visual checkup of his
entire body. The ML should keep track of the character’s
hit points.
</Pain_Insensitivity>
	<Dwarfism type="str">Mutated genes have altered the mutant’s
physical size, an effect either related to a
pituitary defect or a change in the genetic
program during the years of body
growth and development. With this
mutation, the mutant is a dwarf, a
mutant with substantially decreased
size and body weight.

To figure out the character’s size, start
with a base of 6 feet. Roll 1d4+1
and subtract the result from 6 to get
the height of the character in feet.
This will give a range from 1 and 4
feet.

The character’s diminutive size makes
it harder to damage opponents, but
also makes it more difficult for opponents to land
successful blows on the mutant, since he presents such a
small target. A dwarf mutant has a +1 to hit targets of
human sized or larger with a non-powered hand weapon.
He does -1 to damage for every 1’ shorter than he is from
3 feet, with an equal reduction (improvement) of AC for
each foot he is shorter than 3’.
</Dwarfism>
	<Psionic_Flight type="str">The character may fly through the air with a movement of
up to WIL x 10. Any encumbrance will hinder the
movement by reducing the speed at a level set by the ML.
</Psionic_Flight>
	<Optic_Emissions type="str">This mutation takes two forms. Roll 1d6, and on a roll of
1-3 the mutant character receives the ability to project a
flash of very bright light from the eyes (bright eyes),
blinding an opponent within 30’ for 1d4 rounds. This
blindness causes the opponent a penalty of -4 to attack
rolls and increases his armor class by 4. This ability is
useful regardless of daytime or nighttime. On a roll of 4-6,
the character has the ability to discharge a burst of
radiation from the eyes (gamma eyes), that can reach 30’.
Damage is determined at character creation by rolling for
the class of the radiation on the radiation table in the
Adventuring section.
</Optic_Emissions>
	<Increased_Balance type="str">The character will never fall or stumble, and can climb
almost any surface without being in danger of losing
balance.
</Increased_Balance>
	<Epidermal_Susceptibility type="str">The epidermis of the mutant becomes defective in some
way, either causing 1d6 hp of damage for coming into
contact with usually harmless substances (such as water),
or adding +1 per die of damage caused by specific injury,
such as by fire, radiation, slashing weapons, or
penetrating weapons.
The mutation can also be something that constantly
creates a serious inconvenience for the character, such as
glowing skin, uncontrollable pigment shifting, or skin that
always attracts certain kinds of vermin or larger creatures.
</Epidermal_Susceptibility>
	<Night_Vision type="str">Individuals with this mutation can see in complete
darkness to a range of 60 feet by utilizing minute amounts
of available light. Vision is in black and white only, and
does not function in utter darkness underground, since
some small light must be present (starlight, moonlight),
even if it is so dim normal sight does not perceive it.
</Night_Vision>
	<Natural_Armor type="str">This mutation indicates that the character has grown a
natural defense mechanism over the entire body. It can be
thick fur, scales, a shell, or even rubbery skin. This armor
is moderate (1-3 on 1d6) or extreme (4-6 on 1d6).
Moderate armor grants an AC of 6, while extreme natural
armor grants an AC of 4, but reduces movement to 75%
of its regular rate.
</Natural_Armor>
	<Reflective_Cellular_Structure type="str">The plant’s skin is essentially impenetrable to a randomly
determined form of energy. Roll 1d8; 1-2 electricity; 3-4
heat; 5-6 cold; 7-8 radiation.
</Reflective_Cellular_Structure>
	<Possession type="str">The mutant may wrest control over another creature’s
body, subjecting himself to all of the sensations the
possessed creature experiences. If the creature dies while
possessed, the mutant dies as well. During the time he
possesses another body, the body of the mutant is
unconscious and vulnerable to attack. He may relinquish
control of the body at any time, and will return instantly to
his own body.

This power works at a range of 50 feet, but once inside
another body the possessor can travel any distance with
no ill effects.
</Possession>
	<Intellectual_Affinity type="str">Thanks to advanced thinking capabilities, the mutant gains
one of the following abilities (roll 1d6):

1-2 Martial Affinity: +4 to hit in combat and +1d6
damage.

3-4 Tinkerer Affinity: Bonus of 20% to technology rolls.
The character may also make weapons that do extra
damage, up to +4. These weapons take extra long to
build.

5-6 Bartering Affinity: +3 Charisma when trying to sell an
object, and any object sold will yield up to a multiple of
1d4+1 in profits if the person being bartered with can
afford it.
</Intellectual_Affinity>
	<Epidermal_Photosynthesis type="str">Characters with this mutation get energy from the sun,
processing it through their bodies as though it were food.
If they spend long periods of inactivity in direct sunlight,
they will be able to heal wounds more quickly (4x) than the
regular healing rate (1d3 per day of complete rest). When
they are out of the sun (i.e. at night or in a dark cave) they
are forced to move more slowly in order to conserve their
rapidly depleting energy. This reduces their movement to
50% of the normal rate. Such characters are also more
susceptible to cold and heat, and they suffer a –2 penalty
to saving throws versus cold or heat based energy attacks.
</Epidermal_Photosynthesis>
	<Increased_Willpower type="str">The mutant gains 4 points to his WIL, and gains a bonus
of 10% to technology rolls.
</Increased_Willpower>
	<Abnormal_Size type="str">The plant is either much larger than normal or much
smaller than the average specimen. Roll 1d20 and
multiply or divide the plant’s normal size by that number to
arrive at the new abnormal size. See dwarfism and
gigantism for potential size effects on combat.
</Abnormal_Size>
	<Defective_Mind_Reflection type="str">This defect creates a chance that mental attacks attempted
by the mutant backfire, causing injury to him instead of his
enemy. The chance of this occurring is 25%.

In the case of powers that inflict no damage, the Mutant
Lord should find some way to make the power backfire or
become an inconvenience to the character.
</Defective_Mind_Reflection>
	<Regenerative_Capability type="str">When provided with proper rest and food, this mutation
allows the character to recuperate from injury at a
staggering rate. Given time, mutants may re-grow severed
limbs.

The character heals 10 extra hit points per day. If he
should be so unfortunate as to lose a limb or extremity
(and survive), the lost body part will regenerate over a
period of 1d4+2 weeks. A head may never be regrown,
and characters do not regenerate from death.
</Regenerative_Capability>
	<Teleport type="str">This ability allows the mutant to disappear from one
location and appear in a location up to 20 miles distant
without physically crossing the intervening space. If the
mutant has never been to the location he is teleporting to
or is only slightly familiar with it (ML’s discretion) he has a
25% chance of suffering 10d6 damage upon arrival as he
teleports into a space occupied by another object, or
misjudges some aspect of the location. If he is intimately
familiar with his destination or has spent 2d4 hours
conjuring an image of the location in his mind he can
teleport safely.
</Teleport>
	<Dermal_Acid_Sap type="str">The plant’s sap is a concentrated acid that will inflict 3d6
hp damage every round to creatures that come in contact
with it.
</Dermal_Acid_Sap>
	<Force_Screen type="str">This mutation allows the character to create an invisible
field of energy that is difficult to penetrate. The force
screen is close to the mutant’s body, extending only a few
inches from his skin. It is capable of taking 5d6 hp worth
of damage (the ML determines this secretly each time the
power is used) before it collapses, leaving the mutant
unprotected. The power may only be used once per day.
</Force_Screen>
	<Quickness type="str">This mutation makes the mutant much quicker in all
respects. Movement speed is doubled, mental tasks take
half as long to accomplish, and the character may attack
two times per round in physical combat (not mental
combat).
</Quickness>
	<Mental_Barrier type="str">Any mental attacks against this mutant receive a –4
penalty to their attack roll. A character with this mutation
gains the ability to sense other creatures that have mental
mutations at a range of 90 feet. This secondary ability
does not require a roll.
</Mental_Barrier>
	<Animate_Seeds type="str">This mutation allows the seeds of a plant to maneuver
once away from the plant. The seeds can have their own
plant mutations, but will grow up to have the same
mutations as the adult plant that spawned them.
</Animate_Seeds>
	<Unique_Sense type="str">The mutant with a unique sense may detect certain kinds
of phenomenon that are not detectable by the usual
senses. These might include the ability to “feel” radiation
to a distance of 60’, “smell” water within a mile, or sense
when certain kinds of weather are imminent. The player
and Mutant Lord may devise an appropriate sense, and
what its range will be. Some senses may have
corresponding new organs.
</Unique_Sense>
	<key name="Prey_Scent_(Plant)" type="str">The plant sends out waves of scent that attracts predators.
In the case of a mobile, intelligent PC plant, the ML may
increase the chances of encountering some types of
monsters.
</key>
	<Hemophilia type="str">The mutant’s white blood cells are diminished in count, 
preventing him from healing as quickly as a normal 
specimen of his kind. This mutant may only heal 1d3 hp 
every other day. Once the character is injured, he begins 
to bleed profusely, losing 2 hit points per round until the 
wounds can be properly bandaged. 
</Hemophilia>
	<Chameleon_Metamorph type="str">The plant can change color or shape in order to look like
any other kind of plant, but the mass of the plant is
unchanged. If the plant has a level of intelligence it can
alter the color to benefit it in other ways as well (see
chameleon epidermis).
</Chameleon_Metamorph>
	<Pain_Sensitivity type="str">The character’s nervous system is very susceptible to injury,
resulting in all damage to the character being doubled.
</Pain_Sensitivity>
	<Reduced_Fertility type="str">Very few of these plants will exist in one localized area.
With human intervention, this trait can be bred out of a
plant type in a number of generations through the
application of advanced horticulture practices.
</Reduced_Fertility>
	<Increased_Sense type="str">One or more senses is very acute, allowing the mutant to
sense things others may not. Roll 1d10 to determine the
sense.

1-2 Increased Vision: This allows the mutant to see things
as far as 3 miles away if there is a clear line of sight. This
mutation comes with the benefit of ultraviolet vision and
night vision.

3-4 Increased Hearing: A character may distinguish even
the quietest sounds at a range of 180 feet. This also
allows the mutant to pick out sounds from a jumble of
noises. Mutants with increased hearing cannot be
surprised because they will always hear any movement in
their vicinity, and they can listen at a door with success on
a roll of 1-5 on 1d6.

5-6 Increased Smell: A mutant with this mutation can pick
up scents at 180 feet and tell the difference between
various smells even if some seem overwhelming to others.
Creatures that are upwind can never surprise this
character.

7-8 Increased Touch: This increased sense grants +10%
to technology rolls.

9-10 Increased Taste: This ability does not have a range,
but it ensures that a character cannot be poisoned and will
always be able to tell by tasting whether something is
capable of being eaten for nourishment.
</Increased_Sense>
	<Grenade-like_Fruit type="str">Plants with this mutation have pods that are explosive and
deal 2d6 hp damage to creatures within 10’. Upon
exploding, the pod may also release radiation (50%) of a
randomly determined class. The range for this mutation
varies based on the size of the plant, and whether or not it
is capable of moving under its own power. If the plant is
incapable of movement, the pods simply drop near the
base. If the plant is small (1’-2’), there is a 25% chance a
dropped pod will explode. If it is a medium sized plant (3’-
5’) there is a 45% chance, and if it is a tree-sized plant (6
ft. or beyond), there is an 80% chance of detonation when
dropped. Extremely tall plants may have a 100% chance,
or the ML may declare that any size plant has a higher
chance because of the chemical makeup of the pods.

Plants that are capable of movement can throw their own
pods at a range determined by multiplying the plant’s
height x 10 feet.
</Grenade-like_Fruit>
	<Body_Adjustment type="str">The character can heal all of his hit points once every 24
hours. In addition, if the character is in a life or death
situation, this mutation can double his physical attributes
(Strength, Dexterity, movement) for 3d10 rounds.

This power may only be used 1d4 times per week (roll at
character creation).
</Body_Adjustment>
	<Energy_Retaining_Cell_Structure type="str">The mutant’s body has a higher than normal level of
electrical energy coursing through his body, energy which
he can focus into a shock capable of damaging
opponents who touch him. This electrical shock does 3d6
hp damage.
</Energy_Retaining_Cell_Structure>
	<Full_Senses type="str">The plant is capable of utilizing one or more human
senses, or other senses such as sonar, thermal vision or
other unusual senses. It is up to the player and Mutant
Lord to determine how the plant uses them. If this mutation
is rolled more than once, one or more of the acquired
senses may become increased as per the increased senses
physical mutation.
</Full_Senses>
	<Dual_Headed type="str">The mutant has developed a second head next
to the first. He can only be surprised on a roll
of 1 on 1d6. Roll one die for each head
whenever using senses (listening, looking for
traps), choosing the best result.
</Dual_Headed>
	<Thermal_Vision type="str">The character can see the heat generated by living beings,
heat-emitting weapons, or other natural heat sources. This
vision functions to a distance of 60’ if the mutant has
ordinary vision as well, or to 90’ if thermal vision is the
only form of sight the mutant possesses (the eyes emit
infrared radiation to boost the distance). If a mutant has
ordinary vision and thermal vision, the thermal vision is
only usable in darkness, and it takes 1 round to transition
between them. Immense flashes of heat or those coming
from close proximity to the character can be
overwhelming, blinding the character for 2d4 rounds.
</Thermal_Vision>
	<Ability_Boost type="str">Once per day the mutant is capable of concentrating his
mental energy to such a degree that one of his abilities is
doubled for 1d10 consecutive rounds, or he gains +1 to
attack rolls for 1d10 rounds. The character may choose
either of these options each time the mutation is used.
</Ability_Boost>
	<Control_Light_Waves type="str">The character can control light, creating a number of
interesting effects. He can bend light around himself,
becoming invisible, or he may remove all light from a
small area (10’ radius) at a range of 30 feet. He may also
completely dissipate laser fire anywhere within this 30’
range. All of these effects require concentration, such that
the mutant may move at full speed but not attack when
concentrating on using this mutation.
</Control_Light_Waves>
	<Mind_Reflection type="str">The mutant may reflect any mental attack he experiences
back at the attacker, but he still suffers the effects of the
attack. He may only reflect a power that he has been
successfully stricken by, and only as many times as he has
been stricken by it. The reflected power strikes the mind of
the attacker, and it can never target any other creature.
</Mind_Reflection>
	<Damage_Turning type="str">This mutation allows the character to return any incoming
damage to the origin of the attack. For this power to work
the mutant must use every bit of his concentration, taking
no other actions. Any movement of more than one or two
small steps will cause this power to fail.

The power gradually builds up, allowing 3d6 hp worth of
damage to be turned the first round. This increases by 1d6
per round up to a maximum of 20d6 hp worth of damage.
The mutant only takes damage that is above his current hp
level of damage turning. For instance, in the first round the
character rolls 3d6, with a result of 14. He may turn up to
14 hp of damage the first round. The next round he adds
1d6 to the current running total of 14. He can keep the
power working as long as he remains still and
concentrating, and he may maintain concentration when
he receives damage. The mutant cannot turn attacks that
cause no damage. If such powers are successful, they can
interfere with this ability.
</Damage_Turning>
	<Prehensile_Tendrils type="str">These plant growths are capable of movement and a
rudimentary sense of touch. Prehensile tendrils come in
two forms, Simple and Constrictive. Roll 1d6:

1-3 Simple tendrils: These have a randomly determined
(3d6) DEX and are capable of wielding weapons, but are
not strong enough to do damage on their own. Higher
DEX scores are due to aspects of the plant that make it
more dexterous, like sticky fibers and clingy cilia.

4-6 Constrictive Tendrils: These tendrils can do 2d6
damage through constriction and are capable of rapid
movement. A successful attack roll achieves constriction,
and the victim will suffer damage on each consecutive
round.

Because the growth pattern of such plants dictates that the
tendrils grow to full size quickly, even small plants with this
mutation are considered to have tendrils at least 10’ long,
and are capable of growing their tendrils to any length the
ML desires. To randomly determine the length of the
tendrils, simply multiply the base of 10’ by a roll of: 1d6
for small plants, 1d10 for medium sized plants, or 1d20
for large or tree sized plants. PCs with this mutation may
choose the length of their tendrils, but the length should
range from 10’ to 20’.
</Prehensile_Tendrils>
	<Empathy type="str">The character can attune himself to the emotions of other
beings and is capable of instilling emotions in creatures
who are successfully attacked with this mutation. This
mutation has a range of 90 feet.
</Empathy>
	<Increased_Physical_Attribute type="str">One or more physical attributes is increased. Roll 1d6 to
determine the specific effects.

1-2 Increased Strength: The character can summon bursts
of great strength, dealing an extra 3d6 when damaging an
opponent with a hand-to-hand weapon.

3-4 Increased Dexterity: The character’s AC is adjusted by
–2. This bonus is cumulative with any other DEX bonuses.

5-6 Increased Constitution: The character receives
Constitution x2 in extra hit points, and receives +2 to all
saving throws versus poison.
</Increased_Physical_Attribute>
	<Toxic_Weapon type="str">The character is endowed with a weapon that is toxic to
those affected by it. This could be in the form of a gas that
affects everyone in a specific radius, a spray that can affect
a specific target, or a bite/sting that affects a target at a
range of touch. Some common types of toxic weapons are
paralyzing venoms, blinding gasses or sprays, and acidic
bodily fluids. The range or radius of the attack is up to
30’. Any kind of poison must be rolled on the poison table
in the Adventuring section to determine poison class at
character generation, or alternative effects may be
designed with the ML. In general, no attack should exceed
10d6 in damage (with the exception of poisons that may
inflict death).
</Toxic_Weapon>
	<Mind_Thrust type="str">The mutant is capable of firing a bolt of pure mental
energy into the mind of another creature, doing 3d6 hp
damage at up to 50 feet. This ability takes time to
recharge, and can only be used once every two rounds.
</Mind_Thrust>
	<Precognition type="str">The mutant is capable of seeing up to 3 minutes into the
future, but only with respect to dangerous things that will
affect him. If the future indicates that he is going to suffer
some form of damage, he immediately suffers 1d6 hp
damage. If he is confronted with a vision of his death or of
suffering a grievous wound that would take more than 1⁄2
of his hit points, he suffers 2d6 hp damage and
immediately enters a comatose state lasting 1 turn.
</Precognition>
	<Neural_Telekinesis type="str">With this mutation the character can lift or move WILx10
pounds using only the power of his mind. This ability does
not extend to lifting the mutant, however. To the mutant,
using this power feels like lifting the object with his
strength, and so requires some concentration. This ability
has a range of 50 feet, and can only be used to hold
things for 5 rounds before the mutant becomes tired and
must set the objects down. The mutant must rest for 5
rounds before using the power again.

Any use of this mutation on another creature, or objects
carried by another creature, is considered a mental attack
and must be handled accordingly.
</Neural_Telekinesis>
	<Sensory_Deficiency type="str">This mutation indicates that the character suffers from
either blindness or deafness (50%).
</Sensory_Deficiency>
	<Phantasmal_Damage type="str">When the mutant is damaged, his mind radiates waves of
negative energy in a feedback loop through his nervous
system that causes the effective damage from an attack to
be doubled.
</Phantasmal_Damage>
	<Plant_Fragrance_Development type="str">The plant can send out a scent that is enticing to all living
creatures. This scent can be smelled for a range of up to 5
miles in windy conditions, or 90 feet in regular conditions.

The enticing scent overwhelms any creature that fails a
saving throw versus poison. Every creature so enticed will
stay as close to the plant as possible and try to protect it,
even to the point of fighting other creatures that draw
near. Every 5 rounds anyone enticed by the plant’s
fragrance may make another saving throw. Until the victim
is successful, he will stay near the plant until he dies from
severe dehydration or starvation.

The scent itself deals no damage, but the plant may have
other mutations capable of doing so.
</Plant_Fragrance_Development>
	<Accumulated_Resistance type="str">Through years of exposure to a certain substance
(chemicals or radiation, for instance), or concentrated
form of energy (such as heat, cold, or light) in the mutant’s
environment, a resistance against said source has been
accumulated, allowing the mutant to take more damage
from one of these sources.

This mutation gives the mutant a hit point reserve equal to
his total hit points. This hit point reserve is used to take
damage from the substance he is resistant to before it
begins to affect his regular pool of hit points. This separate
pool heals in the same manner and at the same time as
the character’s hit point pool, even if that rate is changed
by other mutations such as acute hyper healing or body
adjustment.
</Accumulated_Resistance>
	<Disintegration type="str">With this powerful mutation, the mutant can completely
destroy matter on a molecular level. Doing so requires so
much energy expenditure, however, that the mutant is
instantly rendered unconscious, with 1 hp left. The total
weight that may be disintegrated is WILx10 pounds and
the range is 90 feet.

It is more difficult to disintegrate dense materials. Multiply
the mutant’s WIL by 3 to find the percentage chance of
disintegrating metals and stone, or by 5 to figure out the
percentage chance of disintegrating wood or living
material.

Once the mutant has used this power, the ML must
determine, via a secret 1d6 roll, how many days it will be
before the power may be used another time.
</Disintegration>
	<Fragrance_Development type="str">The mutant has the ability to produce a subtle yet hypnotic
fragrance. The fragrance is generally derived from
mutated pheromones/hormones (that are emitted at the
mutant’s will), but could come in another form-spores, for
instance. Once per day the mutant can emit a scent that
forces up to 8 HD of creatures, or any single creature with
less than 13 HD (or 13 CON) within 15 feet to save versus
poison or fall into a hypnotic trance for 2d4 rounds.
Victims may be ordered to commit any act that is not
suicidal, up to and including attacking friends.
</Fragrance_Development>
	<Obese type="str">The character suffers from obesity, and his weight is twice 
that of an average individual of his species. The ML may 
apply encumbrance or combat modifiers when it seems as 
though the character’s size would interfere with his abilities 
in any way. It is also possible to choose one body location 
and declare that the fat accumulates there, giving one or 
more limbs a grotesque, bloated shape compared to that 
of the rest of the body. 
</Obese>
	<Combat_Empathy type="str">The character is so attuned to the minute body language
of others that he can tell what they are going to do before
they do it. This gives him a +1 to hit in combat, and +3
hp damage per damage die rolled in a successful attack.
</Combat_Empathy>
	<Frailty type="str">This is a highly variable mutation, and can be used to 
create any number of body weaknesses. Examples include 
brittle bones or susceptibility to bruising. These would 
increase damage by falls or other blunt force trauma by a 
degree decided on by the ML. However, damage should 
usually be increased no more than by +3 per die of 
damage. 
</Frailty>
	<Plant_Natural_Armor type="str">The plant has developed a thicker skin or shell that
provides armor against physical attacks. In all other ways
this mutation resembles natural armor from the
human/animal mutations list.
</Plant_Natural_Armor>
	<Vampiric_Field type="str">This mutation grants the mutant the ability to absorb the
life essence (hit points) from all creatures (friend or foe)
within a foot radius equal to 30+WIL. This power absorbs
2d4 hp per round from all creatures in the radius, and
these absorbed points go into a separate reserve for the
mutant. All damage to the mutant is taken from these
reserved points until they are gone; after this point the
mutant’s regular hp begin to be affected. Stored hp will
disappear after 24 hours.
</Vampiric_Field>
	<Temperature_Control type="str">With this mutation, the character can raise or lower the
temperature of a visible object within a range of 90 feet.
The specific form of the power must be determined at
character generation (50% heat, 50% cold). The mental
nature of this mutation requires concentration, and the
effect is a graduated level of damage equaling 1d6 per
round. The maximum amount of damage that can be
dealt is 10d6 per round. The ML will decide when an
object or being combusts or freezes completely.
</Temperature_Control>
	<Electric_Charge_Generation type="str">The plant can use some of the excess energy not converted
to food into a stored electrical charge capable of
damaging creatures that come in contact with it. This
electrical weapon does 4d6 hp damage, and must be
recharged. The plant will be fully charged again after four
rounds, and may deliver smaller shocks (non-damaging,
but uncomfortable) every round if under constant
harassment by predators or opponents.
</Electric_Charge_Generation>
	<Dual_Cerebellum type="str">The character has 2 fully functional brains that work in
concert. The mutant receives a bonus of 10% to all
technology rolls, and the character receives one extra
random mental mutation that belongs to the extra brain.
Both brains have identical WIL. Having two brains also
helps to protect the mutant from mental attacks. Whenever
the character is the subject of a mental attack, the attacker
must successfully attack each brain.

Note that a character with two brains may or may not
have two heads. One brain may be located in an
unexpected part of the body, or as part of a small, sickly
or undeveloped conjoined twin.
</Dual_Cerebellum>
	<Negative_Empathy type="str">The mutant sends out waves of negative mental energy,
causing anyone with less than 17 Intelligence within a 90’
radius to have a 15% probability of attacking the mutant.
Only one check is necessary per person until they leave
the field and reenter it.
</Negative_Empathy>
	<Nocturnal type="str">The plant is completely motionless during daylight hours.
As soon as the sun dips below the horizon or the plant is in
full shadow for 1d4 rounds, however, it will begin to move
or otherwise act if it is able.
</Nocturnal>
	<Vegetal_Parasite type="str">If the plant can attack and latch onto another creature for
3 rounds (one successful attack roll for three consecutive
rounds), it will maintain control over the creature as long
as the two are in physical contact. Plants will usually use
these controlled bodies for protection or food, and a plant
may control as many creatures as it has limbs to touch
them.
</Vegetal_Parasite>
	<Ultraviolet_Vision type="str">The character can see the UV spectrum and will be able to
see objects that emit this type of energy. This spectrum
includes gamma radiation, x-rays, and other high intensity
radiation. As a result, a character with this vision can see if
areas have a high level of background radiation. At night,
this vision allows a character to see to a distance of 300’.
Since this vision relies on heavy background radiation, it is
not useful underground unless there is a source of
radiation for illumination. If a mutant has ordinary vision
and ultraviolet vision, the ultraviolet vision is only usable in
darkness, and it takes 1 round to transition between each
form.
</Ultraviolet_Vision>
	<Pituitary_Deformation type="str">This defect indicates the pituitary gland of the mutant has
been deformed by mutation, causing unnatural aging.

A character with this defect appears much older than he
really is, generally two to three times his actual age.
Lifespan is also hindered by this deformation, resulting in a
maximum natural lifespan of 40-50 years.
</Pituitary_Deformation>
	<Density_Alteration_of_Others type="str">This mutation grants the ability to instantly alter the body
density of a target, thus shrinking or enlarging, with
maximum enlargement up to twice the natural body size.
Each fraction of a body size change is accompanied by an
equal fraction increase or decrease to armor class and
speed. For example, reduction of size by 1/4 also reduces
(improves) armor class and movement by 1/4. Becoming
twice as large increases armor class by a multiple of two
(to a maximum of 10) and divides movement in half as
well. Note that reduction of body density to 1/8 makes a
character impervious to damage from sharp implements.

This mutation has a range of 90 feet, a duration of 1d4
turns, and cannot be used on the mutant who wields it.
</Density_Alteration_of_Others>
	<Parasitic_Control type="str">If the character can attack and latch onto another creature
for 3 rounds, he or she will maintain control over the
creature as long as the two are in physical contact.
</Parasitic_Control>
	<Poison_Susceptibility type="str">This mutation makes all poisons much more dangerous to
the character. All saving throws versus poison are made
with a penalty of -4.
</Poison_Susceptibility>
	<Metamorph type="str">The character can choose (at character creation) another
creature that he or she can transform into. The character
does not gain the mutations of the creature, just the
physical appearance and natural abilities (such as claws or
sharp teeth). This physical change (in either direction)
takes 2 full rounds of inactivity before it is complete.
</Metamorph>
	<Shriek type="str">The mutant’s vocal cords are substantially altered,
allowing him to produce sounds both above and below
the normal human auditory range. The culmination of this
ability seems to be a focused shout, using the sonic
vibrations on everyone in the immediate vicinity of the
mutant.

Once per day, the mutant can let out a horrible shriek that
affects everyone within a 10’ radius of him. Targets in the
area of effect must save versus stun attacks or take 1d4
points of sonic damage and be deafened for 1d6+4
rounds. Those who successfully save are unaffected.
Mutants with the mutation echolocation suffer a -2 penalty
to save.
</Shriek>
	<Metaconcert type="str">This ability allows the mutant to link its mind with other
mutants of a similar type or those who have the same
mental mutation. These include those with the
Metaconcert mutation, or other mental mutations that
facilitate control between the minds of two beings. The
mutant may combine his WIL with the WIL of other mutants
for conducting a mental attack, or some other joint
purpose.
</Metaconcert>
	<Complete_Wing_Development type="str">The mutant has developed a complete set of wings, either in the
form of fleshy membranes, feathery wings, bat-like
extremities, or even scaly or insect-like versions. With these
wings the character can fly with a movement of 120’. The
mutant may fly while carrying only 25% of his body weight.
Creatures over 150 pounds cannot use these wings for
flight, but they leap to a distance of 120’, with a maximum
height of 80’.
</Complete_Wing_Development>
	<Aberrant_Form type="str">This mutation covers a wide array of effects over the entire
bodily structure of the mutant. Roll 1d8 to determine the
nature of the mutation.

1-2 Enlarged Parts: Some aspect of the mutant’s body has
grown to an abnormally large size and, as a result, has
increased functionality. Because this is a benefit all limbs
and organs are assumed to be affected in concert (i.e.
both arms, both legs, etc.). For example, this mutation
could manifest as a +1, +2, or +3 to damage if arms
are larger than normal, or +60 to movement for longer or
larger legs.

3-4 Xenomorphism: The character gains a unique
organ/limb with a new function, such as an extra pair of
eyes on stalks, a prehensile proboscis, a limb or body part
from another species, or a set of tentacles that act as extra
arms. An extra body part from another species may (50%)
be equipped with a natural weapon.

5-6 Extra Parts: Any organ or limb that is normally present
may be multiplied. An extra normal organ (extra heart,
extra set of lungs) may be acquired, which could increase
CON by +1. To generate a random number of a given
body part roll 1d4+1 and multiply by that number, or a
number may be selected. The brain and/or head cannot
be duplicated by this mutation. The body part must be
selected at character generation.

7-8 Natural Weapon: The mutant is equipped with a
natural weapon, such as horns, teeth, or claws (select at
character creation). These will inflict damage as
determined by rolling 1d8; 1-2 1d4, 3-4 1d6, 5-6 1d8,
7-8 1d10. The character may only attack once per round
with a natural weapon, unless he possesses more than one
attack per round. A natural weapon may (25%) be
equipped with a toxic weapon, such as poison.
</Aberrant_Form>
	<Plane_Shift type="str">This mutation grants the power to visit realities in other
dimensions. These dimensions are accessed through
temporary doors which the mutant creates using the power
of his mind. These doors appear as large portals 10’x10’
in size, and will last for 6 rounds or until the mutant closes
them intentionally. Once entered, they cannot be exited
without a mutant with this ability opening another door.
The mutant can only choose to open doors to worlds he
has visited before. Otherwise, the doorway leads to a
random world of the ML’s choice and design. This ability
only works once per week.
</Plane_Shift>
	<Natural_Vegetal_Weapons type="str">his mutation covers all types of aspects of a plant that
could generally be considered “natural”. This includes
things like large thorns (up to 12 inches), or sharp leaves
capable of cutting into flesh or clothing. While dangerous
on their own, these will generally only affect characters
that blunder into the plant unaware of its danger. When
such weapons are attached to plants that are capable of
attacking or moving their vines or limbs about, however,
they become very dangerous indeed.

The types of weapons covered by Natural Vegetal
Weapons can do 1d4, 1d6, or 1d8 damage. Determine
randomly for PCs by rolling 1d6; 1-2 1d4; 3-4 1d6; 5-6
1d8. These weapons may have other effects decided by
the ML. They may be passive, or attached to mobile vines.
</Natural_Vegetal_Weapons>
	<Echolocation type="str">The mutant has the ability to gather information on his
surroundings by using a type of natural sonar. The mutant
must emit a noise (some kind of clicking or speech will
do), which then reverberates off of the surface of any
surrounding objects or creatures, is picked up by an
external sense organ and translated into a rough, colorless
picture of all objects in the mutant’s surroundings. This
allows the character to interact with the surroundings as if
he has sight, even if he does not have eyes or regular sight
is obscured. This does not allow the mutant to see through
objects, nor will it allow him to read text or see pictures.
This works for a range of 90 feet, or 270 feet if the
character also has the increased hearing mutation.
Mutants with this ability will have a better chance of
striking an opponent, receiving a +2 to hit in combat.
</Echolocation>
	<Ancestral_Form type="str">This mental mutation can reduce an opponent’s
mutational capabilities, eventually removing all forms of
mutation and returning it to its original, unadulterated
form. On each round after a successful mental attack with
this mutation, the target has one mutation removed
permanently (randomly determined), until none are left.
Rarely (5%), this power allows a powerful mutant to
regress a pure specimen further down the evolutionary
line, to a previous stage of its evolution. For example, a
pure human might become a dimmer-witted Homo
erectus, and onward. This attack may only be attempted
for the duration of one encounter, whether it succeeds or
not, and cannot be used again for 1 week.
</Ancestral_Form>
	<Plant_Accumulated_Resistance type="str">With this mutation, the plant has learned to change its
structure to gain complete immunity to any energy-based
attack that it has experienced in the past, including heat,
cold, electricity, radiation, or energy weapons.
</Plant_Accumulated_Resistance>
	<Animal_Limbs_or_Organs type="str">This mutation gives the plant any kind of organs or limbs
normally found in humans or animals. The player and
Mutant Lord will determine the exact nature of the new
limbs or organs.
</Animal_Limbs_or_Organs>
	<Free_Movement type="str">The plant is capable of maneuvering on its own at
standard movement. This may be through the use of leg-
like protrusions or by pulling itself along the ground with
vines or other branches.
</Free_Movement>
	<Thermal_Emissions type="str">The plant is capable of generating a ray of heat or cold
(50%) capable of doing 4d6 damage to those it comes in
contact with. Depending on the size of the plant, it may
have 1d3 heat or cold emitting flowers or branches. The
range of this attack is 50 feet. The ML may determine if
there is a difference between intelligent plants and other
plants with regard to this power. A suggested difference is
a -2 attack adjustment for plants with no higher order
mental functions.
</Thermal_Emissions>
	<Thermal_Sensitivity type="str">The plant is susceptible to heat or cold (50%). Such energy
based attacks deal 2 extra points per die of damage in
addition to the regular damage inflicted.
</Thermal_Sensitivity>
	<Acute_Hyper_Healing type="str">The character may concentrate his mental energies to
allow him to heal 4x the normal rate. He will also be free
from physical pain and fatigue for up to 24 hours. This
power may be used once per week.
</Acute_Hyper_Healing>
	<Reflective_Epidermis type="str">The character’s skin is essentially impenetrable to a
particular form of energy. At character creation, roll 1d8.
A roll result of 1-2 is electricity, 3-4 is heat, 5-6 is cold,
and 7-8 is radiation. The mutant will never suffer damage
from this energy source.
</Reflective_Epidermis>
	<Dermal_Poison_Sap type="str">The sap of the plant is poisonous to creatures that come in
contact with it or ingest it. The poison effects should be
determined with a roll on the poison table.
</Dermal_Poison_Sap>
	<Simian_Deformity type="str">A mutant who suffers from this mutation has an altered
appearance that mimics that of the great apes (such as
gorillas and chimpanzees) - shorter legs, quadrupedal,
and elongated arms that permit the knuckles to touch the
ground and aid in movement.

The character’s shortened legs reduce his base speed to
2/3 normal. However, if all 4 limbs are used to move
(arms and legs), his speed is normal. A character using his
arms to assist movement cannot be wielding a weapon or
carrying items in his hands.
</Simian_Deformity>
	<Radioactive_Emissions type="str">The plant has become irradiated through mutation, and is
capable of giving off a randomly determined class of
radiation at a range of 150’. A good sized patch of these
plants is capable of clearing a large area of animals and
other radiation sensitive creatures, and will often become
a safe haven for creatures that are immune to the effects
of radiation.
</Radioactive_Emissions>
	<Neural_Telepathy type="str">Using this ability, the mutant can connect his mind with
another creature’s mind and communicate directly, even if
the two creatures speak completely different languages or
are of different species. The range of this ability is 30 feet.
</Neural_Telepathy>
	<Vision_Impairment type="str">This mutation covers all visual impairments that fall short
of total blindness, including macular degeneration,
myopia, severe light sensitivity, cataracts, etc. This
condition makes it extremely difficult for the mutant to
discern objects more than 50 feet away. Characters with
this mutation have a -2 to hit in combat.
</Vision_Impairment>
	<Energy_Ray type="str">Every 3 rounds, this mutation grants the ability to emit a
blast of energy (roll 1d6; 1-2 heat, 3-4 cold, 5 radiation,
6 electricity) from the hands (or other upper appendages)
that inflicts 4d6 hit points of damage to a distance of 50
feet. Only one type of energy may be chosen at character
creation
</Energy_Ray>
	<Projectile_Thorns type="str">The plant is endowed with a substantial number of thorns.
These thorns are capable of being thrown if the plant has
mobility and any level of intelligence. The throwing range
of these thorns is like a dagger, and they deal 1d4 hp
damage if they strike a creature. Some plants (50%) grow
thorns that are covered with toxins. Determine the class of
the poison randomly.
</Projectile_Thorns>
	<Chameleon_Epidermis type="str">The mutant’s outer cellular structure has been mutated,
allowing the cells to actually alter their lucidness,
appearance, and color. In effect, this allows the mutant to
subtly change colors on a cellular level. The being may
hide, if stationary, almost as if invisible. The color change
takes place immediately, and requires no concentration by
the mutant. The Mutant Lord should assign a percentage
chance, based on the situation, that the mutant will not be
noticed when using this camouflage. In complete darkness
or thick cover, the percentage could be 95%, while in
daylight if the character is unmoving it might be 50%.

Characters wearing heavy armor or fully garbed
receive no benefit from Chameleon Epidermis.
</Chameleon_Epidermis>
	<Reduced_Immune_System type="str">Whenever the character falls ill, whether it is from infection
caused by combat/misadventure, or airborne infectious
diseases, the character suffers an extra 10 hp of damage
per day. If using the optional Disease rules characters with
this mutation suffer a -4 saving throw adjustment against
diseases, and the duration is doubled.
</Reduced_Immune_System>
	<Gigantism type="str">Mutated genes have altered the mutant’s physical size, an
effect either related to a pituitary defect or a change in the
genetic program during the years of body growth and
development. While this serves to increase strength and
size potential substantially, the mutant is nonetheless
noticeably different than others of his species.

The original size is based on a 6 foot height. Roll 3d6,
adding that many feet to the size of the mutant, achieving
sizes between 9 and 24 feet. The mutant gets a bonus to
damage, based on his height. Note that all mutants with
gigantism suffer a -1 penalty to hit creatures 3’ tall or
smaller.

Damage Dice Bonus: Height 9’ = +1, 12’ = +2, 18’ = +3, 24’ = +4

*The Damage Dice Bonus is only applicable to non-powered
hand weapons.
</Gigantism>
	<Weak_Will type="str">The WIL of the mutant is reduced to 3.
</Weak_Will>
	<Quick_Mind type="str">The mutant is capable of learning how to use technology
at a much higher rate of speed than other characters (in
1/3 the time), and receives a bonus of 30% to technology
rolls. When confronted with a mental attack, an attacker
must roll to attack three times, succeeding each time (roll
three times for the one attack). Because of his incredible
leaps of logic, a mutant with this ability has a 100%
chance of figuring out whether someone is telling the truth.
</Quick_Mind>
	<Density_Alteration_of_Self type="str">This mutation grants the ability to instantly alter the body
density of a target, thus shrinking or enlarging, with
maximum enlargement up to twice the natural body size.
Each fraction of a body size change is accompanied by an
equal fraction increase or decrease to armor class and
speed. For example, reduction of size by 1/4 also reduces
(improves) armor class and movement by 1/4. Becoming
twice as large increases armor class by a multiple of two
(to a maximum of 10) and divides movement in half as
well. Note that reduction of body density to 1/8 makes a
character impervious to damage from sharp implements.

This mutation has a range of 90 feet, a duration of 1d4
turns, and cannot be used on the mutant who wields it.
</Density_Alteration_of_Self>
	<Bizarre_Appearance type="str">This mutation can take a number of forms. The character’s
hair color, eye color, skin color (or any combination) can
be a color not normally found in humans. Odd hair colors
might be light red, unusually fair blond, white, platinum,
or silvery gray. Skin hues might include extensive freckling,
melanin blotches, irregularly livid tones, etc. Eye colors
could be red, pink, white, unusual flecked combinations
etc. Other mutations are possible, such as scales instead
of skin, general cosmetic deformity, or general animal-like
deformity. Whatever the abnormal condition, it is clear
that the character is not a normal human or animal.
</Bizarre_Appearance>
	<Reduced_Oxygen_Efficiency type="str">This mutation makes it harder for the character to get
oxygen into the circulatory system. This means that, after
any amount of extended physical activity (including
combat) lasting more than 5 rounds, the character must
rest or fall unconscious for 3d6 rounds. Further, when
exploring ruins these characters need to rest for 1 turn
after 3 turns of exploration. See “Rest” in the Adventuring
Rules section.
</Reduced_Oxygen_Efficiency>
	<Increased_Caloric_Needs type="str">This drawback requires the character to eat twice the 
normal amount of food daily. During times of vigorous 
activity, this need becomes more acute. For every 5 rounds 
of vigorous activity, the character must eat for 1 round or 
lose 2 hit points and 1 point of STR each melee round 
until he eats again or until the activity stops. All losses will 
be regained at an equal rate for each round that food is 
consumed, until all loss of hit points and STR is regained. 
</Increased_Caloric_Needs>
	<Prey_Scent type="str">The mutant’s body sends out waves of scent that will
attract predators. The ML may increase the occurrence of
wandering monsters, at his discretion.
</Prey_Scent>
	<Plant_Shriek type="str">Whenever a plant with this mutation is damaged, it gives
off a piercing shriek that is capable of damaging everyone
within a 30’ radius. This strange attack does not harm
other similar plants. The shriek causes 3d6 damage (save
versus stun attacks for half), and may be used every 4
rounds until the plant is killed. Mutants with the
echolocation mutation suffer a -2 penalty to save. If a
large patch of these plants is injured all at once, such as
when they are trampled by large creatures or vehicles roll
3d10 for damage instead of 3d6. An intelligent plant may
use this ability every 4 rounds at will.
</Plant_Shriek>
	<Mental_Phantasm type="str">With this power, the mutant is capable of creating a
realistic, illusory environment in the mind of another
conscious creature. These visions are realistic to all senses
but touch. Once the target tries to make physical contact
with any element of the phantasm it dissolves into reality.
</Mental_Phantasm>
	<Greater_Force_Screen type="str">This force screen can be used at a range of 4’, and is
capable of enclosing other creatures. It can take 5d6 hp
worth of damage before it collapses (the ML determines
this secretly each time the power is used), and can be used
once per day. It can also be employed in the same
manner as the regular force screen.
</Greater_Force_Screen>
	<Atrophied_Cerebellum type="str">The mutant’s brain has atrophied in certain areas due to a
genetic birth defect. As a result of this mutation, the
mutant suffers a one-time –2 reduction of INT and DEX,
due to deterioration in mental capacity and coordination.
</Atrophied_Cerebellum>
	<Control_Weather type="str">The mutant can change the weather in the local area. It
takes 1 round to use the mutation and an additional 1d4
rounds for the effects to manifest. The mutant calls forth
weather appropriate to the climate and season of the
area.

Possible Weather:

Spring = Tornado, thunderstorm, sleet storm, or
hot weather

Summer = Torrential rain, heat wave, or hailstorm

Autumn = Hot or cold weather, fog, or sleet

Winter = Frigid cold, blizzard, or thaw

Late winter = Hurricane-force winds or early spring
(coastal area)

The mutant controls the general tendencies of the weather,
such as the direction and intensity of the wind, but cannot
control specific applications of the weather-where lightning
strikes, for example, or the exact path of a tornado.
Contradictory weather conditions are not possible
simultaneously. Control weather can do away with
atmospheric phenomena (naturally occurring or otherwise)
as well as create them.
</Control_Weather>
	<Know_Direction type="str">The character is incapable of being lost, even if all other
senses are somehow nullified. He will always be able to
find a location where he has been previously, and will
know its relation to any location in which he currently
resides.
</Know_Direction>
	<Phobia type="str">The mutant has an irrational fear of some creature or
object. Whenever he comes face to face with the object of
his fear, he flees immediately, throwing anything in his
hands at the feared object/creature in an effort to distract
or harm it. He will flee in the opposite direction at full
movement for 1d4 rounds.

Roll 1d6 to find out what category his fear falls into. The
ML will flesh out the specifics.

1. Other technological (robots, vehicles)

2. Weaponry (energy weapons, other)

3. Animal

4. Plant

5. Ordinary object

6. Insect

</Phobia>
	<Prehensile_Tail type="str">The mutant has developed a special tail. The tail is not
necessarily a balancing tool, but more of an “additional
limb”.

The tail can grapple objects like a hand (much like a new
world monkey’s tail), allowing the mutant to hang from
tree limbs, for instance, leaving the arms and legs free to
perform other actions of a more complex and agile
nature. Some typical bonuses granted by the mutation
might be a +2 bonus to Dexterity checks when climbing or
balancing (+4 if climbing trees), etc. The tail can also be
used in more mundane ways, such as holding a light
source, so the character can employ both hands to fight.
The tail cannot use weapons or hold a shield, however, as
it is not quite that dexterous.
</Prehensile_Tail>
	<Tripping_Tendrils type="str">These tendrils have a very low strength (1d4), and are
capable of only very slow movement. Given enough time,
however, they can crush a small or weakened creature in
their grasp. Once in position, without resistance, they may
inflict 1d6 hp damage per round. The plant usually grows
a large patch (2d10 feet in diameter) of these vines to trip
victims. Victims who fall unconscious on vines such as
these are not likely to waken.
</Tripping_Tendrils>
	<Poisonous_Spores type="str">Whenever the plant is disturbed, it will emit a cloud of
spores. These spores can cause any effect the player and
Mutant Lord wishes. The most basic type of poisonous
spore simply has a random class of poison, but others may
be hallucinogenic, paralytic, or allergy inducing. All will
allow a saving throw versus poison.
</Poisonous_Spores>
	<Killing_Sphere type="str">This powerful mutation allows the mutant to generate a
25’ radius sphere of deadly mental energy centered on the
mutant. Within this sphere of energy all creatures except
the mutant (friend or foe!) have their hit points reduced to
1 point, and must save versus stun attacks or be knocked
unconscious for 1d10 rounds. After using this mutation,
the mutant is exhausted from the force of the mental
exertion and may move at full rate but not attack for 2d10
rounds.
</Killing_Sphere>
	<Slow_Mutant type="str">This mutation makes the mutant much slower in all
respects. Movement speed is halved, mental tasks take
twice as long to accomplish, and the character may attack
once every other round.
</Slow_Mutant>
	<Dermal_Poison_Slime type="str">The mutant is covered in a thick gooey slime (like a frog)
that is poisonous to those who touch or attempt to ingest
the mutant. Roll on the poison table (see Adventuring
Rules) at character creation for the class of the poison in
the slime. Successful bare-hand attacks and bite attacks
against the mutant require the attacker to attempt a saving
throw versus poison. Bare-hand attacks made by the
mutant have the same effect.
</Dermal_Poison_Slime>
	<Flight type="str">The plant has developed some way of coasting on strong
winds and, if the plant is intelligent, it may have actual
winged flight. The method of flight is up to the ML.
Perhaps the plant has grown special cupped leaves or a
series of light tubules that make it structurally capable of
flight. For winged flight by modified leaves, see complete
wing development for movement. Otherwise, the plant’s
movement rate will be heavily dependent on wind speeds.
</Flight>
	<Carnivore type="str">The plant has mouths that are capable of inflicting 1d8
damage with a bite. Roll 1d12 to determine how many
mouths are on the plant.
</Carnivore>
	<Albinism type="str">This mutation prevents the formation of melanin. The
mutant’s hair and skin are bone white, and his eyes have
light pink irises. Due to the lack of pigment in the eyes, the
being is highly sensitive to light, and suffers a –2 penalty to
hit when in daylight.
</Albinism>
	<Spiny_Growth type="str">rts of the mutant’s body are covered with prickly spines,
which may be small, medium, or large. Roll 1d6 at
character generation to determine the size. Small spines
(1-2) inflict 1d4 damage, medium spines (3-4) inflict 1d6,
and large spines (5-6) are capable of inflicting 1d8
damage. Any type can be removed and thrown as a
dagger. With a little effort, the small spines are capable of
being hidden beneath normal clothing, but the medium
and large spines are virtually impossible to conceal
because of their size.
</Spiny_Growth>
	<Injected_Poison_Sap type="str">The plant has a toxic sap that is injected when the plant’s
branches or vines are stepped on or otherwise blundered
into. A PC with this mutation may use this as an attack
each round. The class of the poison is determined
randomly.
</Injected_Poison_Sap>
</root>
